A Guide to the Drewry Family Papers, 1868-1998 (bulk 1910-1960)
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Drewry Family Papers, 1868-1998 (bulk 1910-1960)
The Library of Virginia
51766
.9 cubic feet (2 boxes) and 11 volumes
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Purchased.
Biographical Information
Patrick Henry Drewry was born in Petersburg, Virginia on 24 May 1875. He graduated from Randolph-Macon College in 1896, and then studied law at the University of Virginia. Drewry was admitted to the bar in 1901 and commenced practice in Petersburg, and was in partnership with Charles T. Lassiter (1870-1930). He was also a director of the Petersburg Savings and American Trust Company. He served in the Virginia State Senate from 1912 to 1920, and was a delegate to the Democratic State Conventions in 1912, 1916, 1920, and 1924, and the Democratic National Convention in 1916. He married Mary Elizabeth Metcalf (1871-1959). Drewry was elected to the U. S. House of Representatives to fill the vacancy caused by the death of Walter A. Watson (1867-1919), and served from 27 April 1920 until his death on 21 December 1947.
His son, John Metcalf "Jack" Drewry was born on 23 December 1911 in Petersburg. He attended Randolph-Macon College and the University of Virginia, and practiced law in New York City. In 1939, he moved to Washington DC, where he served as chief counsel of the U.S. Maritime Commission until 1947. He then served as counsel and chief counsel to the House Merchant Marine and Fisheries Committee until 1969. John M. Drewry married 1) Nancy Tucker Wilson (1912-1995), the daughter of James Southall Wilson and Julia Gardiner Tyler, on 22 December 1938. They divorced in 1950. He married 2) Judith_____ (b. 1927). John Metcalf Drewry died in Alexandria on 18 January 1978.
Scope and Content
Papers, 1868-1998, of Patrick Henry Drewry (1875-1947) of Petersburg, Virginia, and his son John Metcalf Drewry (1911-1978) of Alexandria, Virginia. The bulk of the collection covers the years 1910 to 1960.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Correspondence.
II. Subject Files.
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence., Extent: 1 box. (Box 1)
  Topics of the correspondence include invitations and speaking engagements, Petersburg history, and the marriage of John M. Drewry to Nancy Tucker Wilson in 1938.
  - 1891. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1909. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1910. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1911. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1912. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1913. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 1914. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 1915. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1916. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 1917. (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 1918. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1921. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 1923. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 1924. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1925. (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 1927. (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 1928. (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 1929. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1938. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1939. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 1940. (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 1942. (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 1947. (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1960. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - 1961. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 1962. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - 1982. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Undated. (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Series II. Subject Files., Extent: 2 boxes and 11 volumes. (Box 1-2)
  The subject files include clippings, greeting cards, information on President Franklin D. Roosevelt's judicial reorganization proposal, invitations to keel layings and launchings of numerous ships, materials relating to the reorganization of Petersburg city government in 1917, memorial addresses delivered in Congress upon the death of the Rep. Drewry, photographs, programs, and research notes on Petersburg history, especially Fort Henry, and notable citizens in the area. There are also 11 scrapbooks on Petersburg's history, as well as essays, poetry, literature, and cases in which Rep. Drewry was involved when he was practicing law.
  - Bowers, Claude G. - Speech at Tyler Bust Unveiling, 16 June 1931. (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Fort Henry. (Box 1, Folder 31-33)
  - Genealogical Notes - Various Families. (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Greeting Cards. (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Inaugural Ceremonies, 21 January 1957. (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Invitations. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Judicial Reorganization, 1937. (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Publishing and Press. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Research Notes and Correspondence. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "The Roebuck Family in America" by Bette Dickson Casteel. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Typescript. (Box 3, Folder 12-13)
  - Vital Statistics. (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Wayland. (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Wayland-Gaar-Eheart. (Box 3, Folder 16-17)
- Series III. Plunkett Family Papers., Extent: 4 boxes. (Box 4-7)
  The Plunkett family papers relate to the family of William Franklin Plunkett (1822-1870) of Greene County, Virginia, and his son William Benjamin Plunkett (1849-1905), sister-in-law Tabitha Louisa Gaar (1829-1917) and niece Lizzie Dandridge Eheart (1875-1965). There are accounts and receipts, agreements and contracts, appointments and commissions, bonds and promissory notes, clippings, correspondence, deeds, estate administration records, invitations, memorandum books, photographs, and tax receipts.
  - Account Book, 1867-1873. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Account Book, 1883-1887. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Account Book, 1893-1906. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Accounts and Receipts, 1838, 1840-1930. (Box 4, Folder 4-13)
  - Accounts and Receipts, undated. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Accounts and Receipts - Smith, John A. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Agreements and Contracts. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Appointments and Commissions. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Billfolds. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Board of Supervisors Records. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Bonds and Promissory Notes, 1849-1904. (Box 5, Folder 5-10)
  - Clippings. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Conway Bonds and Receipts. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1856, 1864. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1870-1939, 1950. (Box 5, Folder 13-20)
  - Correspondence, undated. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Deeds, 1807-1923. (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Deposition, 1861. (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Election Records. (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Enterprise Manufacturing Company of Pennsylvania. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Estate of Ann Gaar. (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Estate of George Gaar. (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Estate of Tabitha L. Gaar. (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Estate of James Higdon. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Estate of John Higdon. (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Estate of William Benjamin Plunkett. (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Estate of William Franklin Plunkett. (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Estate of James Shifflett. (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Eyeglass Lenses. (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Fee Bills. (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Gaar v. Thornton - Witness Attendance. (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Garr, John C. (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Gilbert Family Register. (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Greene Humane Society - Receipts. (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Hogs. (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Impressment Records. (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Indemnifying Bond. (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Invitations. (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Land Patent, 1728. (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Memorandum Books. (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Miscellaneous. (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Orders for Payment or Goods. (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Paint Sample Catalog. (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Paper Cuttings. (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Photographs. (Box 7, Folder 1-4)
  - Powers of Attorney. (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Property Exempt from Distress and Levy. (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Recipes. (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Sale Bills, unidentified. (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Schedule of Confederate Money. (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - School Exercises. (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Shifflett v. Ham. (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Stewart Iron Works. (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Suit Papers. (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Survey. (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Tax Tickets and Receipts, 1850-1926. (Box 7, Folder 15-22)
  - Time and Pay Book. (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Will of Robert G. Douglass. (Box 7, Folder 24)
- Series IV. Subject Files., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 8-10)
  The subject files include estate papers, genealogical journals and other published sources, Huguenot Society application papers, information on Revolutionary War soliders from Prince William County, Virginia, research on the Allegre, Carr, and Failes families, proceedings of the Elizabeth McIntosh Hammill Chapter of the Daughters of the American Revolution, a scrapbook, and copies of the Greene County Register newspaper.
  - Adverisement - Chandler and Taylor (Indianapolis, IN) - Side-Cutting Mulay Saw Mill. (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Allegre. (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
  - American History Documents Price List. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Bennett. (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Breedlove. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Carr. (Box 8, Folder 7-8)
  - Carr, George (1800-1886). (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Carter. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Cavaliers and Pioneers - Supplement - Northern Neck Grants No. 1. (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Clippings. (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Confederate Soldiers Buried in Woodlawn Cemetery, Elmira NY. (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution. (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Daughters of the American Revolution - Elizabeth McIntosh Hammill Chapter. (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Estate of John Carr, Sr. (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Estate of Lizzie D. Eheart. (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Estate of Robert Lee Eheart. (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Failes. (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Failes, John S. (Box 8, Folder 20-21)
  - "Federal Population Censuses, 1790-1890" (NARA Catalog). (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - "Genealogical Source Material" - Daughters of the American Revolution Magazine. (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - "William Grayson: An Overview of the Life of One of Virginia's First United States Senators" by Marilyn Nehring. (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - "Great Winterthur Rooms" by John H.A. Sweeney. (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Greene County Register, 9 June 1905, 16 November 1906 (2 copies), 6 March and 24 July 1908. (Box 10, Folder n/a)
  - Huguenot Society. (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - The Journal of Southern History, February, May, November 1978. (Box 9, Folder n/a)
  - Louisa County Historical Magazine, 1978-1979. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Manassas VA Centennial. (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - The New England Quarterly, March and December 1978. (Box 9, Folder n/a)
  - Photograph. (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Piedmont Hospital (Charlottesville, VA). (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Pioneer America Society. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Polk County TX. (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Prince William County Revolutionary War Soldiers. (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Research Notes. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Revolutionary War Pensions of African-Americans. (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Scrapbook. (Box 10, Folder n/a)
  - "A Short History of Ohio Land Grants". (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Sons of Confederate Veterans. (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - United Daughters of the Confederacy -78th Annual Convention Minutes, 1973. (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - United States Naval Institute 1954 Cover Pictures. (Box 10, Folder n/a)
  - Virginia Colonial Churches. (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Genealogical Society Bulletin, 1969. (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Virginia Genealogical Society Bulletin, 1970. (Box 9, Folder 15)